<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Giving back to tech - PowerPoint, PDF</title><link href="https://jentrialgo.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://jentrialgo.github.io/feeds/powerpoint-pdf.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://jentrialgo.github.io/</id><updated>2025-04-30T12:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Publishing PowerPoint presentations with animations as PDFs</title><link href="https://jentrialgo.github.io/publishing-powerpoint-presentations-with-animations-as-pdfs.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-04-30T12:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2025-04-30T12:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>J.E.</name></author><id>tag:jentrialgo.github.io,2025-04-30:/publishing-powerpoint-presentations-with-animations-as-pdfs.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I create PowerPoint presentations, I often use animations to explain complex processes. I design slides so the final state is clear on its own, but sometimes this isn’t feasible. When sharing these presentations as PDFs, animations are lost, making slides hard to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found a solution: &lt;a href="https://github.com/maxonthegit/PPspliT"&gt;PPSplit&lt;/a&gt;, a PowerPoint plug-in that exports presentations with animations as PDFs. PPSpit works by splitting animated slides into multiple PDF pages, each representing a step in the animation sequence. This preserves the flow and context of the presentation, ensuring viewers can follow the intended progression without needing the original PowerPoint file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use PPSpit in Windows, install the plug-in from its &lt;a href="https://www.maxonthenet.altervista.org/ppsplit.php"&gt;web page&lt;/a&gt; and open your presentation in PowerPoint. PPsplit will add a new tab to split the slides. Notice that &lt;em&gt;this changes the file&lt;/em&gt;, so make a copy of the original presentation before using it, especially if you have auto-save enabled. After splitting, you can save the presentation as a PDF. The resulting PDF will have each animation step on a separate page, making …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When I create PowerPoint presentations, I often use animations to explain complex processes. I design slides so the final state is clear on its own, but sometimes this isn’t feasible. When sharing these presentations as PDFs, animations are lost, making slides hard to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve found a solution: &lt;a href="https://github.com/maxonthegit/PPspliT"&gt;PPSplit&lt;/a&gt;, a PowerPoint plug-in that exports presentations with animations as PDFs. PPSpit works by splitting animated slides into multiple PDF pages, each representing a step in the animation sequence. This preserves the flow and context of the presentation, ensuring viewers can follow the intended progression without needing the original PowerPoint file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use PPSpit in Windows, install the plug-in from its &lt;a href="https://www.maxonthenet.altervista.org/ppsplit.php"&gt;web page&lt;/a&gt; and open your presentation in PowerPoint. PPsplit will add a new tab to split the slides. Notice that &lt;em&gt;this changes the file&lt;/em&gt;, so make a copy of the original presentation before using it, especially if you have auto-save enabled. After splitting, you can save the presentation as a PDF. The resulting PDF will have each animation step on a separate page, making it easy to follow along.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="PowerPoint, PDF"></category><category term="PowerPoint"></category><category term="PDF"></category></entry></feed>